Guide to the Beth York Papers, 1968-2015 RL.01423
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Beth York papers
1968-2015
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
York, Beth
RL.01423
9.0 Linear Feet
Musician and academic music therapist. Collection includes manuscripts, sound recordings, and photographs from York's music career, with materials from her participation at the 1986 International Music Festival; press kits with photographs and reviews of her music; contracts and agreements from Ladyslipper Inc.; and materials relating to her album Transformations, released in 1985. Also includes materials documenting academic career including research, teaching, publishing, and grant administration.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Beth York Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2010 and 2018.
Biographical Note
Dr. Beth York (b. 1949) is a Board Certified Music Therapist as well as a musician and performer. Originally from South Carolina, she graduated from the University of Georgia with a Bachelor of Music degree in music therapy in 1972. She later earned her Ph.D. in music education from the University of Miami. Throughout the 1980s, she worked as a performer, a music therapist in various mental health centers, and a music instructor. Her first commercial recording, Transformations, was distributed by Ladyslipper beginning in 1985, and was nominated by the National Association of Independent Record Distributors as a Best New Age Recording.
York's academic career in music therapy began at Utah State University, where she served as director of the music therapy program. Her research has focused on feminist music therapy and music therapy for people with disabilities. In 2005, she was hired to start the music therapy program at Converse College in Spartanburg, South Carolina, where she became a Professor Emerita of Music Therapy in 2018. York has also published extensively on topics such as feminism and the women's music movement.
Collection Overview
Collection includes manuscripts, sound recordings, and photographs from York's music career, with materials from her participation at the 1986 International Music Festival; press kits with photographs and reviews of her music; contracts and agreements from Ladyslipper Inc.; and materials relating to her album Transformations, released in 1985.
Accession 2018-0113 consists of materials documenting York's academic career as a music therapist, including her M.A. thesis, university evaluations and a tenure portfolio, teaching materials, research materials, conference materials, presentations, correspondence, workshop materials, a performance piece called Finding Voice, grant materials, and music therapy workshop materials.
York also co-edited a number of issues of the lesbian feminist quarterly Sinister Wisdom, which are included in the collection, as are production materials, drafts, and correspondence related to those issues. Also included are issues of the women's periodicals Hotwire and Paid My Dues.
Related Material
Ladyslipper, Inc. Records
Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture, Duke University.
Feminist music; Feminism and music -- United States; Music therapy; Photographs; Negatives (photographs); Audiocassettes; Phonograph records; Women musicians; Women singers; Ladyslipper, Inc.; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture; York, Beth; Converse College; Sinister wisdom
- Music Materials, 1968-1998; 1 box
  Scope and Contents note
  Original audio materials are CLOSED to use. Please contact the Rubenstein Library in advance if you are interested in hearing this material.
  - Anima Rising, Atlanta, Georgia, 1978-1985 (Box 1)
    Separated recordings are in Box 2.
  - First National Congress of Women in Music, March 1981 (Box 1)
  - Aurora, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    Includes cassette tape.
  - Artist correspondence, 1983-1988 (Box 1)
  - Collaborations with Kay Gardner (letters and scores), 1985-1998 (Box 1)
  - International Women's Music Festival correspondence, Israel, 1986-1988, 2 folders and 1 t-shirt (Box 1)
  - Investor letters, 1983-1985 (Box 1)
  - Kay Gardner memorials (Box 1)
  - Ladyslipper, Inc., 1985-1986 (Box 1)
    Includes contract, promotions, reports, and 1 cassette tape.
  - Miscellaneous artist contracts, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous performances, 1982-1987 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous therapy workshops, early vita, and letters, 1970-1988 (Box 1)
  - Performance contacts, 1983-1987 (Box 1)
  - Photographs and pictures from concerts, promotions, and rehearsals (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous photographs and negatives, 1978-1985 (Box 1)
  - Press kit materials, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Projects and grant proposals, 1979-1987 (Box 1)
  - Southern Arts (media and education project) concert, 1989 October 21 (Box 1)
  - Transformations, first concerts, 1981-1983 (Box 1)
  - Transformations, Ladyslipper, 1985-1986 (Box 1)
  - Transformations, reviews and articles, 1983-1987 (Box 1)
  - Women's music business, 1984-1986 (Box 1)
  - Test presses of records (3 records) (Box 2)
  - Transformations title drafts and notes (Box 2)
  - Press Kit, 1983-1999 (Box 5)
  - Publicity, 1970-1983 (Box 5)
  - Poetry, 1968-1971 (Box 5)
  - Lucina's Music and Orchid Productions (Box 3)
  - Atlanta Feminist Women's Chorus, 1983-2014 (Box 3)
  - Women's International Music Series, 1986 (Box 3)
- Academic Materials, 1978-2015
  - Finding Voice: A Performance Piece, 2006; Includes CD (Box 4)
  - Reactions to Finding Voices, 2003-2004 (Box 4)
  - AAUW Grant, 2003 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 2003-2004 (Box 4)
  - Performances, 2003-2004 (Box 4)
  - Music Therapy Workshops, 1980s (Box 4)
  - M.A. Thesis, University of Miami, 1993-1995 (Box 5)
  - Residual Music Skills Test, 1994 (Box 5)
  - World Congress of Music Therapy Conference, 1999 (Box 5)
  - Professional Evaluations, Converse College, 1995-2015 (Box 5)
  - Tenure Portfolio, Converse College (Box 5)
  - Music Therapy Course Materials, 2014 (Box 5)
  - Paid My Dues: A Quarterly Journal of Women in Music, 1978-1980 (Box 5)
  - Hot Wire: The Journal of Women's Music and Culture, 1986-1989 (Box 5)
  - Sinister Wisdom Issues #102-104, 2017 (Box 3)
  - Interviews and Transcripts for Sinister Wisdom #104, 2017 (Box 3)
  - Sinister Wisdom #104 Working Draft, 2016 (Box 3)
  - Southern Lesbian Herstory (Box 3)
  - CeCe Mitchell Interview (Box 3)